Each of you possesses
كل منكم يمتلك
the most powerful, dangerous and subversive trait
أقوى صفة خطيرة ومدمرة
that natural selection has ever devised.
ابتكرها الانتخاب الطبيعي.
It's a piece of neural audio technology
هي جزء من تقنية عصبية سمعية
for rewiring other people's minds.
لإعادة تشكيل أذهان البشر.
I'm talking about your language, of course,
أتكلم عن لغتكم، بالطبع،
because it allows you to implant a thought from your mind
لأنها تتيح لكم أن تزرعوا فكرة من عقولكم
directly into someone else's mind,
مباشرة في عقل شخص آخر،
and they can attempt to do the same to you,
وهم قد يحاولوا فعل الشيء نفسه لك،
without either of you having to perform surgery.
دون أن يضطر أي منكما لإجراء جراحة.
Instead, when you speak,
بدلاً من ذلك، عندما تتحدث،
you're actually using a form of telemetry
أنت في الحقيقة تستخدم نوع من القياس عن بعد
not so different
ليس مختلف كثيراً
from the remote control device for your television.
عن جهاز التحكم عن بعد الخاص بتلفازك.
It's just that, whereas that device
الفرق أنه، بينما ذاك الجهاز
relies on pulses of infrared light,
يعتمد على نبضات من الأشعة فوق الحمراء،
your language relies on pulses,
تعتمد لغتك على نبضات،
discrete pulses, of sound.
نبضات مباشرة من الصوت.
And just as you use the remote control device
وتماماً كما تستخدم جهاز التحكم
to alter the internal settings of your television
لتغير الإعدادات الداخلية بتلفازك
to suit your mood,
لتواءم مزاجك،
you use your language
أنت تستخدم اللغة
to alter the settings inside someone else's brain
لتغير الإعدادات في دماغ شخص آخر
to suit your interests.
ليتواءم ورغباتك.
Languages are genes talking,
اللغات هي الجينات عندما تتحدث،
getting things that they want.
لتحصل على الأشياء التي تريدها.
And just imagine the sense of wonder in a baby
وتخيل الإحساس بالذهول لدى مولود
when it first discovers that, merely by uttering a sound,
عندما يكتشف لأول مرة أنه، فقط بترديد صوت،
it can get objects to move across a room
يمكن للأشياء أن تتحرك في غرفة
as if by magic,
وكأنما تتحرك بفعل السحر،
and maybe even into its mouth.
وربما تنتهي الأشياء لفمه حتى.
Now language's subversive power
بالطبع قوة اللغات المدمرة
has been recognized throughout the ages
كانت معروفة عبر العصور
in censorship, in books you can't read,
من خلال الرقابة، ثمة كتب لا يمكنك أن تقرأها،
phrases you can't use
عبارات لا تستطيع استخدامها
and words you can't say.
وكلمات لا يمكنك قولها.
In fact, the Tower of Babel story in the Bible
في الحقيقة، قصة برج بابل في الإنجيل
is a fable and warning
هي أسطورة محذرة
about the power of language.
من قوة اللغة.
According to that story, early humans developed the conceit
تبعاً للقصة، استبد الغرور بالبشر القدماء
that, by using their language to work together,
لحد أنهم، باستخدام لغتهم عملوا معاً،
they could build a tower
ليبنوا برجاً
that would take them all the way to heaven.
ليأخدهم جميعاُ إلى الجنان.
Now God, angered at this attempt to usurp his power,
والإله، الغاضب من هذه المحاولة للتعدي على سلطته،
destroyed the tower,
دمّر البرج،
and then to ensure
ومن ثم ليضمن
that it would never be rebuilt,
أنه لن يعاد بناءوه أبداً،
he scattered the people by giving them different languages --
فرق الناس بإعطاءهم لغات عديدة --
confused them by giving them different languages.
حيّرهم بمنحهم لغات مختلفة.
And this leads to the wonderful irony
وهذا أدى للمفارقة المذهلة
that our languages exist to prevent us from communicating.
في أن لغاتنا تمنعنا من التواصل.
Even today,
حتى اليوم،
we know that there are words we cannot use,
نعلم أن هناك كلمات لايسعنا استخدامها،
phrases we cannot say,
وعبارات لايمكننا أن نقولها،
because if we do so,
لإننا إن فعلنا،
we might be accosted, jailed,
قد نُعنف، نسجن،
or even killed.
أو حتى نقتل.
And all of this from a puff of air
وكل هذا بسبب نفحة من هواء
emanating from our mouths.
خارجة من أفواهنا.
Now all this fuss about a single one of our traits
كل هذا الضجيج عن واحدة من صفاتنا
tells us there's something worth explaining.
يخبرنا أن هناك ماهو جدير بالتقصي.
And that is how and why
وهو كيف ولماذا
did this remarkable trait evolve,
هذه الصفة المميزة تطورت،
and why did it evolve
ولماذا تطورت
only in our species?
فقط في جنسنا (نحن البشر)؟
Now it's a little bit of a surprise
حسناً الأمر المفاجئ نوعاً ما
that to get an answer to that question,
أنه للحصول على إجابة لهذا السؤال،
we have to go to tool use
لابد أن ندرس استخدام الأدوات
in the chimpanzees.
عند قردة الشمبانزي.
Now these chimpanzees are using tools,
تستخدم الشمبانزي أدوات،
and we take that as a sign of their intelligence.
ونحن نرى هذا دليلاً على ذكاءها.
But if they really were intelligent,
ولكنها لو كانت فعلاً ذكية،
why would they use a stick to extract termites from the ground
لماذا تستخدم عصا لتستخرج الأرضة (النمل) من الأرض
rather than a shovel?
بدلاً من استخدام معول؟
And if they really were intelligent,
وإذا كانوا فعلاً أذكياء،
why would they crack open nuts with a rock?
لمَ يضربون المكسرات بحجر ليكسروها؟
Why wouldn't they just go to a shop and buy a bag of nuts
لمَ لا يذهبون للمتجر ويشترون كيساً من المكسرات
that somebody else had already cracked open for them?
قام شخص آخر بكسرها وتقشيرها لهم؟
Why not? I mean, that's what we do.
لمَ لا؟ أليس هذا ما نفعله.
Now the reason the chimpanzees don't do that
السبب أن الشمبانزي لا تفعل هذا
is that they lack what psychologists and anthropologists call
هو أنهم يفتقدون لما يسميه اخصائيو علم النفس والأنثروبولوجي
social learning.
التعلم الاجتماعي.
They seem to lack the ability
يبدو أنهم يفتقدون القدرة
to learn from others
على التعلم من الآخرين
by copying or imitating
بالمحاكاة أو التقليد
or simply watching.
أو فقط بالمشاهدة.
As a result,
وكنتيجة،
they can't improve on others' ideas
لا يمكنهم أن يزيدوا على أفكار الآخرين
or learn from others' mistakes --
أو أن يتعلموا من أخطاءهم --
benefit from others' wisdom.
الإستفادة من حكمة الآخرين.
And so they just do the same thing
وبالتالي هم يفعلون الشيء نفسه
over and over and over again.
مراراً ومراراً.
In fact, we could go away for a million years and come back
للأمانة، نستطيع أن نغيب لملايين السنين ونعود
and these chimpanzees would be doing the same thing
وستظل هذه القردة تفعل الشيء نفسه
with the same sticks for the termites
بنفس العصا بحثاً عن الأرضة
and the same rocks to crack open the nuts.
وبنفس الحجار لكسر المكسرات.
Now this may sound arrogant, or even full of hubris.
قد يبدو هذا متعالياً أو مليء بالفوقية.
How do we know this?
كيف نعرف هذا؟
Because this is exactly what our ancestors, the Homo erectus, did.
لأنه بالضبط مافعله سابقونا، إنسان الهومو اركتس (الإنسان المنتصب).
These upright apes
هذا الإنسان الأشبه بقرد مستقيم
evolved on the African savanna
تطور في السافانا الأفريقية
about two million years ago,
قبل مايقارب مليوني عام،
and they made these splendid hand axes
وهم صنعوا تلك النصال البديعة
that fit wonderfully into your hands.
والتي تناسب شكل يدك ببراعة.
But if we look at the fossil record,
ولكن لو نظرنا لتاريخ الأحافير،
we see that they made the same hand axe
سنجد أنهم صنعوا نفس النصل اليدوي
over and over and over again
مراراً ومراراً
for one million years.
لمليون سنة.
You can follow it through the fossil record.
بإمكانكم تتبع هذا من تاريخ الأحافير.
Now if we make some guesses about how long Homo erectus lived,
لو خمنا كم سنة عاشوها بشر الهومو اركتس،
what their generation time was,
تقديراً على معدل سنوات العمر في أجيالهم،
that's about 40,000 generations
سنجد أنهم تقريباً 40,000 جيل
of parents to offspring, and other individuals watching,
من الأباء إلى الأبناء وهم يراقبون آباءهم،
in which that hand axe didn't change.
وفي كل هذه الأجيال لم يتغير النصل.
It's not even clear
ليس حتى واضحاً
that our very close genetic relatives, the Neanderthals,
أن أقرب الأجناس لنا جينياً، بشر النياندرتال،
had social learning.
كان لديهم تعلم اجتماعي.
Sure enough, their tools were more complicated
بالتأكيد، كانت أدواتهم أكثر تعقيداً
than those of Homo erectus,
من تلك التي لدى الهومو اركتس،
but they too showed very little change
ولكنهم هم أيضاً أظهروا القليل جداً من التغيير
over the 300,000 years or so
خلال مايقارب الثلاثمئة ألف سنة
that those species, the Neanderthals,
التي عاشوها
lived in Eurasia.
في قارة أوراسيا.
Okay, so what this tells us
حسناً، مايخبرنا به هذا
is that, contrary to the old adage,
أنه، بنقيض المقولة القديمة
"monkey see, monkey do,"
"القردة ترى، القردة تفعل"،
the surprise really is
المفاجأة الحقيقة هي
that all of the other animals
أن كل الحيوانات الأخرى
really cannot do that -- at least not very much.
فعلاً لاتستطيع فعل ذلك -- على الأقل ليس كثيراً.
And even this picture
وحتى هذه الصورة
has the suspicious taint of being rigged about it --
قد يشوبها نوع من التزوير --
something from a Barnum &amp; Bailey circus.
شيء من سيرك بانم وبيلي.
But by comparison,
لكن بالمقارنة،
we can learn.
نحن نستطيع أن تعلم.
We can learn by watching other people
نتعلم بمشاهدة الناس الآخرين
and copying or imitating
وتقليد أو محاكاة
what they can do.
مايستطيعون فعله.
We can then choose, from among a range of options,
يمكننا بعدها أن نختار، من عدة خيارات،
the best one.
أيها أفضل.
We can benefit from others' ideas.
نستطيع أن نستفيد من أفكار الآخرين.
We can build on their wisdom.
نستطيع أن نبني على معارفهم.
And as a result, our ideas do accumulate,
وكنتيجة، أفكارنا تتراكم،
and our technology progresses.
وتقنياتنا تتطور.
And this cumulative cultural adaptation,
وهذا التأقلم الثقافي التراكمي،
as anthropologists call
كما مايسميه الأنثروبولوجيون
this accumulation of ideas,
هذا التراكم في الأفكار،
is responsible for everything around you
مسؤول عن كل شيء حولك
in your bustling and teeming everyday lives.
في حياتك اليومية الصاخبة.
I mean the world has changed out of all proportion
أعني أن العالم تغير تماماً بكل المقاييس
to what we would recognize
عما كنا لنعرفه
even 1,000 or 2,000 years ago.
حتى قبل ألف أو ألفي سنة مضت.
And all of this because of cumulative cultural adaptation.
وكل هذا حدث بفعل التأقلم الثقافي المتراكم.
The chairs you're sitting in, the lights in this auditorium,
الكراسي التي تجلسون عليها، الإضاءة في هذا المسرح،
my microphone, the iPads and iPods that you carry around with you --
المايكروفون الخاص بي، الأيباد والأيبود التي تحملونها معكم
all are a result
كلها نتائج
of cumulative cultural adaptation.
للتأقلم الثقافي المتراكم.
Now to many commentators,
لكثير من المعلقين،
cumulative cultural adaptation, or social learning,
التأقلم الثقافي المتراكم، أو التعلم الاجتماعي،
is job done, end of story.
هو نهاية الحكاية.
Our species can make stuff,
جنسنا يستطيع صنع أشياء،
therefore we prospered in a way that no other species has.
ولأجلها نحن ازدهرنا بشكل لم يحدث لأي جنس آخر.
In fact, we can even make the "stuff of life" --
في الواقع نحن نصنع "أدوات الحياة" --
as I just said, all the stuff around us.
كما قلت، كل الأشياء حولنا.
But in fact, it turns out
ولكن الحقيقة، كما تبين
that some time around 200,000 years ago,
أنه في وقت ما تقريباً قبل 200,00 سنة مضت،
when our species first arose
عندما نهض جنسنا لأول مرة
and acquired social learning,
وتحصلوا على التعلم الاجتماعي،
that this was really the beginning of our story,
كانت هذه فعلاً بداية حكايتنا،
not the end of our story.
وليس نهايتها.
Because our acquisition of social learning
لأن حصولنا على التعلم الاجتماعي
would create a social and evolutionary dilemma,
كان ليسبب معضلة اجتماعية وتطورية،
the resolution of which, it's fair to say,
وحلها، من العدل القول،
would determine not only the future course of our psychology,
كان ليقرر ليس فقط مستقبل سايكولوجيتنا،
but the future course of the entire world.
بل مستقبل العالم بأسره.
And most importantly for this,
والمهم في هذا،
it'll tell us why we have language.
أنه سيخبرنا لماذا لدينا لغات.
And the reason that dilemma arose
والسبب أن تلك المعضلة ظهرت
is, it turns out, that social learning is visual theft.
أن التعلم الاجتماعي ماهو إلا سرقة بصرية.
If I can learn by watching you,
إذا كنت أستطيع التعلم عبر مراقبتك/ مشاهدتك،
I can steal your best ideas,
أستطيع أن أسرق أفضل أفكارك،
and I can benefit from your efforts,
وأستطيع أن أستفيد من جهودك،
without having to put in the time and energy that you did
دون أن أحتاج لأضع الوقت والطاقة التي وضعتها أنت
into developing them.
في صنع الأشياء.
If I can watch which lure you use to catch a fish,
وإذا كنت أستطيع مشاهدة أي طعم تستخدم أنت لصيد سمكة،
or I can watch how you flake your hand axe
أو كيف تشحذ نصلك اليدوي
to make it better,
لتجعله أفضل،
or if I follow you secretly to your mushroom patch,
أو إذا تبعتك سراً لمحصولك من الفطر،
I can benefit from your knowledge and wisdom and skills,
أستطيع الاستفادة من معرفتك ومهاراتك،
and maybe even catch that fish
وربما أصيد تلك السمكة
before you do.
قبل أن تفعل.
Social learning really is visual theft.
التعلم الاجتماعي هو سرقة بصرية.
And in any species that acquired it,
وفي أي جنس يحصل عليه،
it would behoove you
سيتوجب عليك
to hide your best ideas,
أن تخبئ أفضل أفكارك،
lest somebody steal them from you.
لئلا يسرقهم منك شخص آخر.
And so some time around 200,000 years ago,
وبالتالي قبل نحو 200,000 سنة مضت،
our species confronted this crisis.
جنسنا واجه هذه المشكلة.
And we really had only two options
وكان لدينا فعلياً خيارين
for dealing with the conflicts
للتعامل مع الأزمات
that visual theft would bring.
التي كان سيجلبها السطو البصري.
One of those options
أحد هذين الخيارين
was that we could have retreated
هو أننا كنا نستطيع أن ننكفئ
into small family groups.
لمجموعات عائلية صغيرة.
Because then the benefits of our ideas and knowledge
لأنه وقتها الفائدة من أفكارنا ومعرفتنا
would flow just to our relatives.
سيذهب فقط لاقربائنا.
Had we chosen this option,
لو كنا اخترنا هذا الخيار،
sometime around 200,000 years ago,
قبل 200,000 سنة،
we would probably still be living like the Neanderthals were
لكنا على الأرجح مازلنا نعيش كما عاش النينادرتال
when we first entered Europe 40,000 years ago.
عندما دخلنا أوروبا قبل 40,000 سنة.
And this is because in small groups
وذلك لأنه في المجموعة الصغيرة
there are fewer ideas, there are fewer innovations.
هناك أفكار أقل، وابتكارات أقل.
And small groups are more prone to accidents and bad luck.
والمجموعات الصغيرة عرضة أكثر للحوادث والحظ السيء.
So if we'd chosen that path,
وإذن لو كنا اخترنا هذا الدرب،
our evolutionary path would have led into the forest --
طريق تطورنا كان ليقودنا للغاب --
and been a short one indeed.
كان ليكون طريقاً قصيراً.
The other option we could choose
الخيار الثاني الممكن
was to develop the systems of communication
كان تطوير نظم الاتصالات
that would allow us to share ideas
التي تسمح لنا بمشاركة الأفكار
and to cooperate amongst others.
وبالتعاون بين بعضنا البعض.
Choosing this option would mean
اختيار هذا الخيار يعني
that a vastly greater fund of accumulated knowledge and wisdom
أن الغالبية العظمى من المعرفة والحكمة المتراكمة
would become available to any one individual
ستكون متاحة لأي فرد
than would ever arise from within an individual family
أكثر بكثير مما ستتيحه عائلة بمفردها
or an individual person on their own.
أو شخص بمفرده.
Well, we chose the second option,
حسناً، نحن اخترنا الخيار الثاني،
and language is the result.
واللغة كانت النتيجة.
Language evolved to solve the crisis
تطورت اللغة لتحل مشكلة
of visual theft.
السطو البصري.
Language is a piece of social technology
اللغة جزء من تقنية اجتماعية
for enhancing the benefits of cooperation --
لتعزز فوائد التعاون --
for reaching agreements, for striking deals
للوصول لاتفاقات، وعقد صفقات
and for coordinating our activities.
ولتنسيق نشاطاتنا.
And you can see that, in a developing society
وبإمكانك أن تروا أنه، في مجتمع نامي
that was beginning to acquire language,
كانت تلك البداية للحصول على لغة،
not having language
عدم وجود لغة
would be a like a bird without wings.
كان ليكون أشبه بالطائر بلا أجنحة.
Just as wings open up this sphere of air
تماماً كما الأجنحة تفتح أثير السماء
for birds to exploit,
للطائر ليستكشفها،
language opened up the sphere of cooperation
اللغة فتحت مدى من التعاون
for humans to exploit.
ليستكشفه البشر.
And we take this utterly for granted,
نحن أخذنا هذا كشيء مسلم به،
because we're a species that is so at home with language,
لأننا جداً معتادين على اللغة.
but you have to realize
لكن علينا أن ندرك
that even the simplest acts of exchange that we engage in
أن أبسط أفعال التبادل التي نمارسها
are utterly dependent upon language.
معتمدة تماماً على اللغة.
And to see why, consider two scenarios
ولنر لماذا، تخيلوا حادثتين
from early in our evolution.
من وقت بعيد في تطورنا.
Let's imagine that you are really good
لنتخيل أنك فعلاً جيد
at making arrowheads,
في صنع رؤوس الحربة،
but you're hopeless at making the wooden shafts
لكنك سيء في صنع عصا الحربة الخشبية
with the flight feathers attached.
بربطها بالريش.
Two other people you know are very good at making the wooden shafts,
اثنان آخران تعرفهما جيدين جدا في صنع العصا،
but they're hopeless at making the arrowheads.
لكنهما سيئان في صنع الرؤوس.
So what you do is --
إذن ما تفعله هو --
one of those people has not really acquired language yet.
أحد هذين الشخصين لم يمتلك لغة بعد.
And let's pretend the other one is good at language skills.
ولنتخيل أن الآخر جيد جداً في المهارات اللغوية.
So what you do one day is you take a pile of arrowheads,
وإذن ماتفعله أنك تأخذ كومة من رؤوس الحرب،
and you walk up to the one that can't speak very well,
وتمضي للشخص الذي لا يستطيع التحدث جيداً،
and you put the arrowheads down in front of him,
وتضع الرؤوس أمامه،
hoping that he'll get the idea that you want to trade your arrowheads
متأملاً أنه سيدرك فكرة أنك تريد أن تقايضه بالرؤوس
for finished arrows.
مقابل حرّب مكتملة.
But he looks at the pile of arrowheads, thinks they're a gift,
لكنه ينظر لكومة الرؤوس، معتقداً أنها هدية،
picks them up, smiles and walks off.
يأخذها، يبتسم ويمضي.
Now you pursue this guy, gesticulating.
بالتأكيد ستتبع هذا الشخص متساءلاً.
A scuffle ensues and you get stabbed
وسيبدأ الشجار بينكما وتُطعن
with one of your own arrowheads.
بإحدى الرؤوس التي صنعتها.
Okay, now replay this scene now, and you're approaching the one who has language.
حسناً الآن أعيدوا عرض هذا المشهد، أنت الآن تنشد الشخص الذي يملك لغة.
You put down your arrowheads and say,
تضع أمامه الرؤوس وتقول،
"I'd like to trade these arrowheads for finished arrows. I'll split you 50/50."
"أريد أن أقايض هذه الرؤوس بأسهم مكتملة. سنتقاسمها النصف بالنصف".
The other one says, "Fine. Looks good to me.
الآخر يقول، "حسناً يبدو عرضاً جيداً بالنسبة لي.
We'll do that."
سأفعل هذا".
Now the job is done.
الآن العمل مكتمل.
Once we have language,
بمجرد أن تصبح لدينا لغة،
we can put our ideas together and cooperate
نستطيع أن نجمع أفكارنا معاً ونتعاون
to have a prosperity
لتزدهر حياتنا
that we couldn't have before we acquired it.
بطريقة لم تكن لتحدث قبل اللغة.
And this is why our species
وهذا هو السبب الذي جعل جنسنا
has prospered around the world
يزدهر في أنحاء العالم
while the rest of the animals
بينما بقية الحيوانات
sit behind bars in zoos, languishing.
تقبع خلف القضبان في حدائق الحيوان.
That's why we build space shuttles and cathedrals
لأجل هذا نبني المراكب الفضائية والكاثدرائيات
while the rest of the world sticks sticks into the ground
بينما بقية العالم مازال يحفر الأرض بالعصي
to extract termites.
ليستخرج الأرضة.
All right, if this view of language
حسناً، لو كانت هذه النظرة للغات
and its value
وأهميتها
in solving the crisis of visual theft is true,
في حل أزمة السطو البصري صحيحة،
any species that acquires it
أي جنس سيحصل على لغة
should show an explosion of creativity and prosperity.
سيظهر دفقاً من الإبداع والإزدهار.
And this is exactly what the archeological record shows.
وهو بالضبط ما تظهره السجلات الأركلوجية.
If you look at our ancestors,
لو نظرتم لأسلافكم،
the Neanderthals and the Homo erectus, our immediate ancestors,
النيناتدرال والهومو اركتس، السلالات التي سبقتنا مباشرة،
they're confined to small regions of the world.
كانوا محدودين بمناطق صغيرة من العالم.
But when our species arose
ولكن عندما ظهر جنسنا
about 200,000 years ago,
قبل 200,000 سنة مضت،
sometime after that we quickly walked out of Africa
في وقت قريب من خروجنا من أفريقيا
and spread around the entire world,
انتشرنا حول كل العالم،
occupying nearly every habitat on Earth.
محتلين تقريباً كل مكان قابل للسكنى في الأرض.
Now whereas other species are confined
بينما كانت الأجناس الأخرى محدودة
to places that their genes adapt them to,
بالأماكن التي مكنتهم جيناتهم من التأقلم فيها،
with social learning and language,
نحن بواسطة التعلم الاجتماعي،
we could transform the environment
نستطيع تغيير البيئة
to suit our needs.
لتتماشى مع حاجاتنا.
And so we prospered in a way
ولذا نجحنا بطريقة
that no other animal has.
لم تحدث لأي حيوان آخر.
Language really is
اللغة فعلاً هي
the most potent trait that has ever evolved.
أقوى صفة منذ تطورنا.
It is the most valuable trait we have
وهي أثمن صفة لدينا
for converting new lands and resources
لنحول بها الأراض الجديدة والموارد
into more people and their genes
ليعيش أناس -بجينات- أكثر
that natural selection has ever devised.
مما كان الإختيار الطبيعي ليبتكر.
Language really is
اللغة فعلاً هي
the voice of our genes.
صوت جيناتنا.
Now having evolved language, though,
لكننا بامتلاكنا لغة متطورة،
we did something peculiar,
فعلنا شيئاً غريباً،
even bizarre.
أو حتى شاذ.
As we spread out around the world,
بينما كنا ننتشر حول العالم،
we developed thousands of different languages.
طورنا آلاف اللغات المختلفة.
Currently, there are about seven or 8,000
حالياً، هناك مايقارب 8,000
different languages spoken on Earth.
لغة مختلفة منطوقة على الأرض.
Now you might say, well, this is just natural.
الآن، قد تقولون، هو أمر طبيعي.
As we diverge, our languages are naturally going to diverge.
كما نتباعد، من الطبيعي أن تتباعد لغاتنا.
But the real puzzle and irony
لكن اللغز والمفارقة الحقيقية
is that the greatest density of different languages on Earth
أن أكبر كثافة للغات في الأرض
is found where people are most tightly packed together.
توجد حيث كم كبير من الناس يعيشون معاً.
If we go to the island of Papua New Guinea,
لو ذهبنا لجزيرة غينيا الجديدة،
we can find about 800 to 1,000
نستطيع أن نجد 800 إلى 1,000
distinct human languages,
لغة إنسانية مستقلة،
different human languages,
لغات مختلفة تماماً،
spoken on that island alone.
منطوقة على تلك الجزيرة وحدها.
There are places on that island
هناك مناطق في تلك الجزيرة
where you can encounter a new language
حيث تصادف لغة جديدة
every two or three miles.
على مسافة ميلين أو ثلاثة أميال من اللغة السابقة.
Now, incredible as this sounds,
كما هو من المذهل سماع هذا،
I once met a Papuan man, and I asked him if this could possibly be true.
فإني قابلت مرة مواطن غيني، وسألته هل من الممكن أن يكون هذا صحيحاً.
And he said to me, "Oh no.
وهو قال، "لا.
They're far closer together than that."
الأمر أكثر مما تتخيله".
And it's true; there are places on that island
نعم:هناك أماكن على الجزيرة
where you can encounter a new language in under a mile.
تصادف فيها لغة جديدة في أقل من مسافة ميل.
And this is also true of some remote oceanic islands.
والأمر أيضاً ينطبق على بعض الجزر البعيدة في المحيط.
And so it seems that we use our language,
وإذن يبدو كما لو أننا نستخدم اللغة،
not just to cooperate,
ليس فقط لنتعاون،
but to draw rings around our cooperative groups
بل لنرسم حدوداً لمدى التعاون بين مجموعاتنا
and to establish identities,
ولنكون هوياتنا،
and perhaps to protect our knowledge and wisdom and skills
وربما لنحفظ معرفتنا وحكمتنا ومهاراتنا
from eavesdropping from outside.
من التنصت عليها من الخارج.
And we know this
ونحن نعرف هذا
because when we study different language groups
لأننا حينما ندرس مجموعات لغوية مختلفة
and associate them with their cultures,
ونربطها بثقافاتها،
we see that different languages
نرى أن اللغات المختلفة
slow the flow of ideas between groups.
تبطئ تنقل الفكرة بين المجموعات.
They slow the flow of technologies.
تبطئ انتقال التقنيات.
And they even slow the flow of genes.
ويمكنها أيضاً أن تبطئ انتقال الجينات.
Now I can't speak for you,
أنا لا يمكنني التحدث باسمكم،
but it seems to be the case
لكن يبدو أن
that we don't have sex with people we can't talk to.
أننا لا نستطيع ممارسة الجنس مع أناس لانعرف كيف نتكلم معهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now we have to counter that, though,
علينا أن نقر رغم هذا،
against the evidence we've heard
برغم الأدلة التي سمعناها
that we might have had some rather distasteful genetic dalliances
قد تكون هناك بعض المداعبات الجينية الغير محمودة
with the Neanderthals and the Denisovans.
بين رجل النينادرتال والمرأة الهومو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay, this tendency we have,
حسناً، هذه النزعة التي نملكها،
this seemingly natural tendency we have,
النزعة الطبيعية،
towards isolation, towards keeping to ourselves,
نحو الإنعزال، والحفاظ على خصوصياتنا،
crashes head first into our modern world.
تتحطم في عصرنا الحديث.
This remarkable image
هذه الصورة المميزة
is not a map of the world.
ليست لخريطة العالم.
In fact, it's a map of Facebook friendship links.
هي في الواقع خريطة لصلات الصداقة في الفيسبوك.
And when you plot those friendship links
وعندما ترسم هذه الصلات
by their latitude and longitude,
حسب موقعها،
it literally draws a map of the world.
هي حرفياً ترسم خريطة للعالم.
Our modern world is communicating
عالمنا الحديث يتواصل
with itself and with each other
مع نفسه وبين الناس
more than it has
أكثر مما فعل
at any time in its past.
في أي وقت مضى.
And that communication, that connectivity around the world,
وهذا التواصل، الاتصال بنواحي العالم،
that globalization
تلك العولمة
now raises a burden.
تحمل عبئاً.
Because these different languages
لأن كل اللغات المختلفة
impose a barrier, as we've just seen,
تشكل عائقاً، كما رأينا،
to the transfer of goods and ideas
في وجه نشر السلع والأفكار
and technologies and wisdom.
والتقنيات والمعرفة.
And they impose a barrier to cooperation.
وتشكل عبئاً في سبل التعاون.
And nowhere do we see that more clearly
ونحن الآن نرى هذا بوضوح
than in the European Union,
في الإتحاد الأوروبي
whose 27 member countries
الذي تتحدث الدول أعضاؤه السبعة والعشرون
speak 23 official languages.
23 لغة مختلفة.
The European Union
الإتحاد الأوروبي
is now spending over one billion euros annually
ينفق الآن مايفوق المليار يورو سنوياً
translating among their 23 official languages.
للترجمة بين هذه الثلاثة وعشرين لغة الرسمية.
That's something on the order
وهو مايقارب
of 1.45 billion U.S. dollars
1.45 مليار دولار
on translation costs alone.
على نفقات الترجمة وحدها.
Now think of the absurdity of this situation.
فكروا في غرابة هذا الموقف.
If 27 individuals
لو كان هناك 27 شخص
from those 27 member states
من هذه السبعة وعشرين دولة عضو
sat around table, speaking their 23 languages,
جلسوا حول طاولة، متحدثين 23 لغة.
some very simple mathematics will tell you
بحسبة رياضية بسيطة أستطيع أن أخبركم
that you need an army of 253 translators
أنكم ستحتاجون جيشاً من 253 مترجم
to anticipate all the pairwise possibilities.
ليسدوا الحاجة لكل الترجمات الممكن طلبها.
The European Union employs a permanent staff
الإتحاد الأوروبي يوظف مترجمين دائمين
of about 2,500 translators.
يصل عددهم لـ 2,500 مترجم.
And in 2007 alone --
وفي 2007 لوحدها --
and I'm sure there are more recent figures --
وأنا متأكد أن هناك أرقام أحدث من هذه --
something on the order of 1.3 million pages
ماكان ليحتاج 1.3 مليون صفحة لو كتب
were translated into English alone.
كان حجم ما ترجم للإنجليزية وحدها.
And so if language really is
وإذن لو كانت اللغة فعلاً
the solution to the crisis of visual theft,
حلاً لأزمة السطو البصري،
if language really is
لو كانت اللغة
the conduit of our cooperation,
وسيلة لتعاوننا،
the technology that our species derived
وتقنية جنسنا ابتكرها
to promote the free flow and exchange of ideas,
ليعزز الانتقال والتبادل الحر للأفكار،
in our modern world,
في زمننا الحديث،
we confront a question.
نواجه سؤالاً.
And that question is whether
والسؤال هو ما إذا
in this modern, globalized world
في هذا العالم العصري،
we can really afford to have all these different languages.
نستطيع تحمل تكاليف كل هذه اللغات.
To put it this way, nature knows no other circumstance
أو لأضع التساؤل بهذا الشكل، الطبيعة لا تعرف ظرفاً
in which functionally equivalent traits coexist.
تتعايش فيه صفتان متعادلاتان معاً.
One of them always drives the other extinct.
لابد لواحدة منهما أن تتطور والأخرى تندثر.
And we see this in the inexorable march
ونحن نرى هذا في المسيرة العتيدة
towards standardization.
نحو توحد الصفات.
There are lots and lots of ways of measuring things --
هناك العديد من طرق قياس الأشياء --
weighing them and measuring their length --
وزنهم وقياس طولهم --
but the metric system is winning.
ولكن النظام المتري هو الذي تسيد.
There are lots and lots of ways of measuring time,
هناك العديد من طرق قياس الوقت،
but a really bizarre base 60 system
لكن النظام الستيني الغريب
known as hours and minutes and seconds
المعروف بالساعات والدقائق والثواني
is nearly universal around the world.
هو تقريباً الموحد في كل العالم.
There are many, many ways
هناك العديد، العديد من الطرق
of imprinting CDs or DVDs,
لطباعة الأقراص المدمجة أو الدي في دي،
but those are all being standardized as well.
لكنها كلها الآن غدت موحدة كذلك.
And you can probably think of many, many more
وبإمكانكم ربما التفكير في المزيد
in your own everyday lives.
من حياتكم اليومية.
And so our modern world now
وإذن عالمنا الحديث الآن
is confronting us with a dilemma.
يواجهنا بمعضلة.
And it's the dilemma
وهي المعضلة
that this Chinese man faces,
التي يواجهها الرجل الصيني،
who's language is spoken
والتي لغته يتحدث بها
by more people in the world
أكثر عدد من الناس
than any other single language,
في العالم،
and yet he is sitting at his blackboard,
ومع هذا هو جالس على لوحه،
converting Chinese phrases
يحول العبارات الصينية
into English language phrases.
إلى أخرى إنجليزية.
And what this does is it raises the possibility to us
ومايفعله هذا هو أنه يرفع الاحتمالية
that in a world in which we want to promote
أنه في عالم نريد أن نعزز فيه
cooperation and exchange,
التعاون والتبادل،
and in a world that might be dependent more than ever before
وعالم نعتمد فيه أكثر من ذي قبل
on cooperation
على التعاون
to maintain and enhance our levels of prosperity,
لنحافظ على ونزيد من معدلات ازدهارنا،
his actions suggest to us
أفعاله تقترح علينا
it might be inevitable
أنه قد يكون أمر حتمي
that we have to confront the idea
أن نتقبل فكرة
that our destiny is to be one world with one language.
أن مصيرنا سيكون عالم واحد بلغة واحدة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Matt Ridley: Mark, one question.
مات رايدلي: سؤال واحد يا مارك.
Svante found that the FOXP2 gene,
سافانتي وجد أن الجين FOXP2،
which seems to be associated with language,
والذي يعتقد أنه مرتبط باللغة،
was also shared in the same form
مشترك أيضاً بالشكل نفسه
in Neanderthals as us.
بين إنسان النينادرتال وبيننا.
Do we have any idea
هل لدينا أي فكرة
how we could have defeated Neanderthals
كيف أننا تفوقنا عليهم
if they also had language?
لو كانوا هم أيضاً لديهم لغة؟
Mark Pagel: This is a very good question.
مارك بيقل: هذا سؤال جيد جداً.
So many of you will be familiar with the idea that there's this gene called FOXP2
أغلبكم سيكون ملماً بفكرة أن هناك جين يدعى FOXP2
that seems to be implicated in some ways
يبدو على صلة بأكثر من طريقة
in the fine motor control that's associated with language.
بالتحكم الحركي الدقيق المرتبط باللغة.
The reason why I don't believe that tells us
السبب الذي لا أعتقد أن وجوده يدلنا
that the Neanderthals had language
على أن النينادرتال كانت لديهم لغة
is -- here's a simple analogy:
أنه -- إليكم تمثيلاً بسيطاً للفكرة:
Ferraris are cars that have engines.
سيارات الفيراري لديها محركات.
My car has an engine,
سيارتي بها محرك،
but it's not a Ferrari.
لكنها ليست فيراري.
Now the simple answer then
الإجابة البسيطة لهذا
is that genes alone don't, all by themselves,
أن الجينات، لا تستطيع لوحدها،
determine the outcome
أن تحدد النتيجة
of very complicated things like language.
لأشياء معقدة مثل اللغة.
What we know about this FOXP2 and Neanderthals
ما نعرفه عن الجين والنينادرتال
is that they may have had fine motor control of their mouths -- who knows.
أنهم ربما كان لديهم تحكم حركي دقيق بأفواههم -- من يدري.
But that doesn't tell us they necessarily had language.
لكن هذا لا يخبرنا بالضرورة أنه كان لديهم لغة.
MR: Thank you very much indeed.
مات رايدلي: شكراً جزيلاً لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)